A Guide to the René Jules Dubos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA122
Rockefeller Archive Center
- MEMORABILIA (Box 94)
  - D Sc. Clark University (with photo), 1970
  - D Sc. Benedictine College (framed), 1974
  - Honorary member American Society for Microbiology
  - Honorary Fellow American School Health Assoc. (2 copies)
  - Large photograph while receiving Arches of Science Award, 1966
  - 2 posters advertising B.Y. Morrison Memorial Lecture "Humanizing the earth" Mounted photo—used for publication, 1972
  - Honorary fellow — American Public Health Association, 1969
  - Honorary Member 1st Conferencia Interamericana de Leprologia Experimentale, 1961
  - 1 roll of original drawings for tables in 1968 Journal of Experimental Medicine article "Lasting biological effects" v. 130 no. 5
  - Appointment by Richard Nixon to Citizen Advisory Committee on Environment Quality, 1973-1974
- Miscellaneous, 20½ × 16¼ × 4" (Flat oversize box). [GL 8/86] (Box 95)
  Photographs, mounted and unmounted, some art work, 1 item original correspondence, one complete issue of Look containing article by R.J. Dubos. Includes:.
  - 1 4x5 photograph in black and white, "School of Athens" Christmas Lectures. [Written on back of photo]
  - Obermann, Hannah/R.J. and Mrs. Dubos [re] conditions in post war Germany and the value of the Dubos' friendship to her, 1947 September 2
    Original handwritten correspondence.
  - Miscellaneous prints
    1 print in color of Sir Thomas More by Holbein.
    1 etching?, Goya, "Escapan entra las Uamas.".
  - Dubos, "The Dreams of Reason"
    1 photograph. Francisco Goya, "The Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters." [Printed on cover of The Dreams of Reason. Note written on back of photograph.].
    1 photograph. Pub "July 13" 1799 by H. Humphrey, 87, St. James's Street.
  - Issue of Look, p. 34, René Dubos one of "Five Who Care", 1970 April 21
  - Dubos, R.J., "The Professor, The Institute and DNA". Photographs. Mariner's Church on Henry Street. 2 photographs, one of which is mounted
    - The Avery family, Photocopy of photograph
    - RU Hospital and Avery in uniform WWI, Photocopy of photograph
    - O.T. Avery in laboratory sitting and inscribed by Avery. Photograph
    - O.T. Avery lab group. Seated left to right: T. Francis, O.T. Avery, W.F. Goebel. Standing left to right: Unidentified, unidentified, R.J. Dubos, Baber
    - p. 12 of what appears to be from an original Avery ms re "Declaration of Scientific Principles"
  - Dubos, R.J., "The Unseen World", 3 folders
    Photographs for use or possible use.
    - Photographs (Box 95, Folder 1)
      - Robert Koch, 1843-1910
      - Robert Koch, 1892
      - Altar to R. Koch in Japan
      - Van Leewenhoek, 2 photographs
    - Photographs (Box 95, Folder 2)
      Old Chapel-Lane, Skibbereen.
      Funeral at Shepperton Lakes.
      Entrance to Dunmanway, From the Bridge on the Cork Road.
      Woman Begging at Clonakilty.
      The Village of Mienies.
      Mullins Hut, at Scull.
      Boy and Girl at Cahera.
    - Scientific photographs, mounted and unmounted and some art work (Box 95, Folder 3)
      - Ballon à col de cygne - Pasteur - demonstration that all bacteria killed - ... Photograph
      - Représentation de cristaux taillés dans le bois par Pasteur. Photograph
      - Lichens. 1 mounted black and white and 1 in color, on cover of Scientific American, 1959 October
      - Flasks containing agar. 1 mounted photograph
      - Stained preparation of specillum. Photographs a and b
      - Section of a germinating seed. 1 mounted photograph
      - 2 unidentified mounted photographs and some art work
  - Wizard Playing a Flute and Representations of Animals. Les Trois-Frères. Print
  - Lister, [Joseph], Mounted photograph. [Broken]
  - Koch, Robert Dr., Tuberkulin, 1892. Mounted photograph
- Honorary Doctor of Medicine, from Université de l'Etat, Liege, Belgium to R.J. Dubos, 1940 (Package 1)
- Galley proof of "The Professor, The Institute and DNA" (Package 2)
- "The Centennial Lectures". Commemorating the 100th Anniversary of E.R. Squibb & Sons, 1959. G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York (Volume 1)
  Presentation by Dubos, "External Environment and Susceptibility to Infection" pp 1-14.
- Dubos, René, "Louis Pasteur". Charles Scribner's sons, New York. Originally published in 1950 and then in 1976, 1950 1976 (Volume 2)
- MEMORABILIA, (package) (Package 3-7)
  Package containing 4 rolls of assorted citations and diplomas. Each roll is labelled with the contents. Total contents are listed below.
  - D Sc. The Rockefeller University, 1975
  - D Sc. Dartmouth College, 1960
  - Honorary member Asociacion Mexicana de Microbiologia, 1956
  - Ph. D. Rutgers University, 1927
  - R.E. Dyer Lectureship Award NIH, 1953 October 22
  - D Sc. Kenyon College
  - D Sc. Rutgers University, 1949
  - Certificate of Advanced Medicine and Surgery, 1976
  - American Society of Contemporary Medicine and Surgery
  - Research Award American Pharmaceutical Manufacturers' Association, 1952
  - Membership American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Mass. [Information as to st (Mass.) by Jean Dub, 1960
  - Doctor of Laws Queens University, Canada, 1968
  - Doctor Humane Letters Yeshiva University, 1961
  - D Sc. St Peters College, 1976
  - D Sc. University of Pennsylvania, 1965
  - Richard Nixon Citation for service on Citizens Advisory Committee for Environmental Protection, 1969
  - Doctor of Letters Thomas Jefferson University, 1974
  - Member Phi Rho Sigma, 1958
  - Member American Philosophical Society, 1954
  - D Sc. National University of Ireland, 1955
  - Foreign Member Academia de Cienias, Fisicas, Matematica y Naturales — Venezuela, 1950
  - University of Notre Dame, 1981
- 10 film reels, #1 thru #10, 1986 May 6; 16mm, 1/2" film, [GL 8/86]
  Identification of reels by Carol Moberg and technical information by John Sholtis, Graphic Services.
  - Profile of Dr. Dubos. WABC-TV, Melba Tolliver, Reporter, 1970 October 19-20; moving image, 17 min. in color and sound (Reel 1)
    Aired 12 Aug. filmed.
    Views of RU, Dr. Dubos' office and laboratory.
    In laboratory discussing his work and 1968 Two Cultures award from Flushing High School, New York City, as most important award Dr. Dubos received. It hangs in his office at RU. 1968.
    Walking around neighborhood of RU w/Melba Tolliver and Jean Dubos.
    Waterfront.
    Shoes worn by Dr. Dubos purchased at Alexander's for $1.50.
    Dubos apartment w/treasures and furnishings.
    Deals with problems today with awareness of continuity of history (an awareness of past.).
  - "René Dubos' Provocative New York", 1969 February 19; moving image, 15 min, in color and sound (Reel 2)
    Dr. Dubos w/Earl Ubell. WCBS-TV (Spring 1969) May have been filmed on Feb. 19 and aired in spring.
    Produced by Osborn Segerberg.
    Reporter, Earl Ubell.
    On RU campus, coming to work, in Dubos laboratory of environmental biomedicine -.
    re destruction of environment, mismanagement of urban life and management of waste.
    Deterioration of city - too much noise and crowding.
    Cities all over the world more crowded than New York - like Hongkong. Dr. Dubos doesn't consider crowding such a problem - one can have a peaceful, crowded life.
    Sameness of environment of city life helps child develop.
    Suburban child not exposed to as much as city child.
    Children learn to deal with problems.
    Management of waterways - air pollution - massive exploration of effects of pollution on children.
    Waterfront along East River Drive - R.J. Dubos and Earl Ubell.
  - Dr. Alex Kessler, "Mouse study". Part of doctorial thesis, 1965-1966; moving image, 4 minutes, no sound, in color (Reel 3)
    Shows what crowded conditions provoke in mice:.
    Violence, Catatonic state, and homosexuality.
    Dr. Dubos not in this film.
  - "Dynamics of Phagocytosis of Staphylococci". Never used by Dubos D.E. Roger and Marian Ann Meely, Dept of Medicine, Vanderilt University, Date?; moving image, No sound, black and white (Reel 4)
    [Carol Moberg. "Possibly for James Hirsch 1964. RU Christmas Lectures and/or earlier than 1964].
  - IV Sound film - [slip inside of metal container] b&w 16 mm, 15 minutes "The Story of Pencillin", Date?; moving image (Reel 5)
    Not rewound - needs spare spool - cannot view until rewound. Dubos used in 1959 Christmas lecture.
  - "Koch film III", Date?; moving image, 5 minutes, black and white, NO SOUND (Reel 6)
    [Carol Moberg, "Used for 1959 Dubos Christmas Lectures or 1964 James Hirsch Christmas Lectures].
    Shows growing tuberculosis on potatoes and plating bacteria.
  - Section from 'The Unborn Patient' for René Dubos, Date?; moving image, 16 mm, color fading (Reel 7)
    Not on a reel - Must be put on reel to be viewed.
    1 BBC television film. Sound cassette available.
  - Section from 'The Unborn Patient' for René Dubos, Date?; moving image, 16 mm, color fading (Reel 8)
    2 BBC film. Not on a reel - must be put on reel to be viewed. sound Cassette available.
  - "Life of the Molds" Chas. Pfizer & Co. Inc., circa 1959?; moving image, No sound, in black and white (Reel 9)
    [Carol Moberg, "Used for Dubos, 1959 RU Christmas Lectures - Dr. Dubos not in film].
    Must be rewound to be viewed.
  - "The Story of Fleischmann 's Irradiated Dry Yeast", circa 1959?; moving image, No Sound, black and white (Reel 10)
    Precision Film Labs.
    [Carol Moberg, "Used for 1959 Dubos Christmas Lectures". Dr. Dubos not in film].
- Additions to the René J. Dubos Papers received from Mrs. Jean Dubos, 13 November 1986, 2.5" letter. [GL 11/86.]
  Correspondence.
  - Biographical Material (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Le Maire de Saint-Brice/R.J. Dubos. (In French) Congratulations re work on tuberculosis, 1947 January 3 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Marois, Président du Conseil, Administration de l'institut de la Vie/Dubos. re 1972 Prize, 1972 May 2 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Bennett, James N. /R.J. Dubos. [re] winning first Institute of Life prize, 1972 May 4 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Bales, Georg C. /Dubos. [re] 1976 Tyler Award, 1976 March 2 (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947 1968 1969 1970-1974 1976 1979 1980-1986
    Much of this correspondence is posthumous and replies (not in our files) by Mrs. Jean Dubos. Some addressed to René J. Dubos at René Dubos Center for Human Environment.
    - A-B (Box 96, Folder 2)
    - C-D (Box 96, Folder 3)
      Selected items:.
      - Leslie Doeffler/R.J. Dubos. re Dubos course "The Wooing of the Earth" at Bard College and student enjoyment of, 1978 December 13
      - Hugh Downs/Dubos. [re] Dubos participant in Today show during its environment week, 1970 May 8
    - E-G (Box 96, Folder 4)
    - H, J-K (Box 96, Folder 5)
      Paul Horgan/R.J. Dubos.
      - [re] Dubos lecture on tulipomania, 1965 January 12
      - [re] Award from Institut de la Vie, 1972 May 3
      - [re] Dubos lecture, 1974 April 3
      - Teddy Kollek/R.J. Dubos. [re] Dubos lecture in Haifa, 1973 April 16
    - L-P (Box 96, Folder 6)
    - R-S (Box 96, Folder 7)
      - R.J. Dubos/Howard Rusk re Rusk autobiography "A World to Care For" and Dubos' concept of rehabilitation, 1981 December 30
        Howard Rusk's reply, Jan. 29, 1982.
    - U-W, 1969 July 1 (Box 96, Folder 8)
      Henry Wolf/R.J. Dubos. [re] Dubos speech at Aspen Conference.
    - [re] Global 2000 Report and Environmental Policies. Dubos views on (Box 96, Folder 9)
    - Photocopies of correspondence (Box 96, Folder 9)
      Includes some handwritten letters by R.J. Dubos. Includes:.
    - Exchange (Box 96, Folder 9)
      - R.J. Dubos/Coleman McCarthy (The Washington Post, Washington, DC), circa 1981 December 18
      - R.J. Dubos/John Adams (NRDC). Enclosures, 1981 December 18
      - Sam Nilsson/ R. Dubos and 1981 July 7. Wm. K. Reilly/R.J. Dubos, 1981 June 2
      - R.J. Dubos/Rufus Miles, 1981 December 18
      - Rufus E. Miles/R.J. Dubos, 1982 January 22
    - Greeting/Post Cards (Box 96, Folder 10)
      Includes handwritten notes. Selected Items:.
      - Paul Horgan/René. New Years Greetings w/ Encl: Newsclip, 1973 Jan. 2. Albuquerque Journal, Editorial, "Human Care is Needed". re René Dubos, 1973 January 5
      - Melba Tolliver, ABC News/René J. Dubos. Picture postcard of Paris scene w/note re beauty of Paris, 1970 August 29
      - Melba Tolliver and Howard Weinberg, WABC-TV/René J. Dubos. re The Institute of Life Award, 1971 May 3
    - Cards. Christmas/New Year Greetings. From (Box 96, Folder 11)
      - Spiro and Judy Agnew
      - Hubert and Muriel Humphrey
      - Leopold (Former King of Belgium) and Princess Lillian
      - Richard and Pat Nixon
    - Book Review by R.J. Dubos. Robert Cassidy, "Margaret Mead. The Later Years", 1981 December (Box 96, Folder 12)
      R.J. Dubos/Sarah Montague (Universal Books) handwritten letter containing statement (review) of book.
    - Clipping (Magazine) (Box 96, Folder 13)
      G.B. Wetterberg, G.T. Prance and T.E. Lovejoy, "Conservation Progress in Amazonia: A Structural Review." Parks, ca 1981, pp 5-10.
- Galley Proof of Dubos, R.J. and Escande, Jean-Paul, "Quest", 2.5" letter [GL 11/86] (Box 105)
  Eliminated, see Box 124.
- Dubos reprints and some by others from Dubos department. Extra copies of. In 2 Paige boxes
  - Reprint #'s 3 - #179. [Not a complete set] (Box 97)
  - Reprint #'s 180 - #610, [Not a a complete set], 1973 1974 1977-1981 (Box 98)
- Glass slides in 4x4 black slide boxes. Each box is string tied. In 2 Paige boxes
  - Slide boxes I - VII (Box 99)
  - Slide boxes VIII - XIV and slide index in binder (Box 100)
- Additions received from Mrs. Jean Dubos, 1987 January 21 1987 January 27; [GL 8/86]
  - Binder with typescript of "The Wooing of the Earth" (Box 101)
  - Envelope with assorted letter and correspondence, including re René J. Dubos travels and Pulitzer Prize, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 101)
  - Memorabilia: Assorted medals and placques (not individually inventoried) (Box 101)
  - Diplomas, including Notre Dame, (separate roll)
- untitled (Box 103)
  [formerly Box 96; partially filled] Eliminated, sec R - 1150.
  2x2 slides from Avery book illustrations. [formely box 97].
- Memorabilia (Box 102)
  Medals.
- Framed certificate, plaque (Box 104)
- Oversize material (Box 104)
  See also oversize box, D room.
  Includes photographs used in The Dream of Reason, The Unseen World, The Professor... [Avery], etc.
  - 1) R. Tagore, stamped "Jay Kay Studios, Inc. 218 West 48th St. New York, New York", (map case, folio room)
  - 2) The Venus of Wellendorf, Jay Kay Studios..., (map case, folio room)
  - 3) Color reproduction of religious painting. No identification, (map case, folio room)
  - 4) plans for Dubos Bioshelter, (map case, folio room)
  - 2 framed certificates - oversize
- (AUDIO TAPES)
  - "Rebel Without Cause", unpublished lecture. College of Wooster, Ohio, February 14, 1966 [80 minutes], 1966 February 14; sound (Box 105, Tape 1)
  - "A Modern Ulysses", unpublished lecture. College of Wooster, Ohio, February 16, 1966 [70 minutes; two cassettes, Part 1 and 2], 1966 February 16; sound (Box 105, Tape 2)
  - Part 1 & 2 "The Pursuit of Significance, I. The Natural Sciences", panel discussion for the Centennial Symposium, with René Dubos, Henry Margenau, and Melvin Calvin, moderated by William Keiffer. College of Wooster, Ohio, February 19, 1966 [105 minutes, two cassettes, Part 1 & 2], 1966 February 19; sound (Box 105, Tape 3)
  - "The Biology of the Urban Environment", unpublished lecture and question and answer session. Kalamazoo College, Michigan, January 21, 1971 [75 minutes], 1971 January 21; sound (Box 105, Tape 4)
  - "Creative Stewardship of the Earth", lecture given for Scholar's Day when Dubos received honorary degree; speech is exerpt of the first half of a speech published in Kalamzoo College Review, June 1971, 33 (2): 2-9. Kalamazoo College, January 22, 1971 [45 minutes], 1971 January 22; sound (Box 105, Tape 5)
  - "Nature Without Man", unpublished lecture with question session. University of Calgary, November 8, 1972 [90 minutes], 1972 November 8; sound (Box 105, Tape 6)
  - Part 1 & 2 "Better Life Through Less Energy", Second René Dubos Forum. Seven Springs, 1978 [60 minutes; two cassettes, Tape 1 contains instructions at the beginning of the Forum and Tape 2 contains the summary statement of Dubos at the conclusion of the three day meeting], Spring 1978; sound (Box 105, Tape 7)
  - "In Search of Certainties", unpublished convocation lecture. University of Guelph, Ontario, Canada, June 8, 1979 [15 minutes], 1979 June 8; sound (Box 105, Tape 8)
  - "Radioscopie", interview [in French]. Radio France, Paris, France, May 16, 1979 [60 minutes], 1979 May 16; sound (Box 105, Tape 9)
  - "In Praise of Diversity", unpublished lecture. University of Tennessee, October 1981 [40 minutes], 1981 October; sound (Box 105, Tape 10)
  - "Celebrations of Life", unpublished lecture. University of Tennessee, October 1981 [70 minutes], 1981 October; sound (Box 105, Tape 11)
  - ["The Quality of Human Life"], sound (Box 105, Tape 12)
    See Box 107.
  - ["Freedom", Third Alumni Seminar, 1967], sound (Box 105, Tape 13)
    Missing.
  - ["The Stock Market Observer", portion of television program, June 12, 1969], sound (Box 105, Tape 14)
  - ["Improving on Nature", unpublished lecture. Calif. Institute of Technology, February 1977], sound (Box 105, Tape 15)
  - "The Future of the Planet: Gifts from the Solar and Ecological Age", "The Sun", dialogues between Dean James Morton and René Dubos. Cathedral of St. John the Divine, December 3, 1978 [90 minutes], 1978 December 3; sound (Box 105, Tape 16)
  - "Le Bonheur", Canadian interview program entitled, "Le Voyage". Radio Canada, February 7 and 19, 1982 [100 minutes; two cassettes, 17a and 17b], 1982 February 7 1982 February 19; sound (Box 105, Tape 17a-17b)
  - "Le Bonheur", memorial tribute to René Dubos based on interviews in AT-17 a and b. Radio Canada, November 13, 1983 [50 minutes], 1983 November 13; sound (Box 106, Tape 18)
  - "Poverty as Creation", sermon-dialogue with Dean James Morton. Cathedral of St. John the Divine, March 9, 1975 [45 minutes], 1975 March 9; sound (Box 106, Tape 19)
  - "Prophecy as Anticipation", unpublished lecture, sermon-dialogue with Dean James Morton. Cathedral of St. John the Divine, December 14, 1975 [45 minutes], 1975 December 14; sound (Box 106, Tape 20)
  - "Stones Into Bread: Resources", sermon-dialogue with Dean James Morton. Cathedral of St. John the Divine, February 28, 1977 [28 minutes], 1977 February 28; sound (Box 106, Tape 21)
  - "Dubos Memorial", The Rockefeller University, December 10, 1982, 1982 December 10; sound (Box 106, Tape 23a-23b)
    Speakers include: Zanvil Cohen, Rollin Hotchkiss, William Reilly, James Hirsch, Lewis Thomas, Jean-Paul Escande, Dr. and Mrs. Arthur Sackler, and Joshua Lederberg. [two cassettes; 23a and 23b].
  - "Saint-Brice-sous-Forêt", Ceremony for the installation of commemorative plaques for René Dubos and Edith Wharton, June 23, 1984, 1984 June 23; sound (Box 106, Tape 24)
    Speakers include: Mayor of Saint Brice, Jean-Paul Escande, Cultural Attache of the American Embassy, and V.P. of General Council and Regional Council. Narrated by Francis Dubos (brother of René) [45 minutes].
  - "Téléphone Sonne", radio call in show, France, "8/12/80". Program held before the opening of the Troisèmes Assises de L'Environnement (three day conference), sound (Box 106, Tape 25)
    Dubos answers questions re: how to motivate government and public opinion on environmental issues [45 minutes].
  - "Symbiosis Between Humankind and the Earth", Rockefeller University Friday Afternoon Lecture. The Rockefeller University, May 14, 1976, with introduction by Samuel C. Silverstein [60 minutes], 1976 May 14; sound (Box 106, Tape 26)
  - "Dubos Day, 1985", 1985 February 20; sound (Box 106, Tape 27a-27b)
    [in French] same as AT-28, except all music selections are included. February 20, 1985 [120 minutes, two cassettes; 27a and 27b].
  - "Dubos Day", emission contacts with Jean-Paul Escande - C. Dolto for radio program. Remembrances of Dubos by French colleagues and friends with comments by H. Noufflard, Alistair Cook, Charles E. Cornelius, Paul R. Ehrlich, Stuart C. Finch, Harry Harris, Jean Mayer, Wilson K. Talley, René J. Dubos, and Kenneth L. Vaux, sound (Box 106, Tape 28)
  - "Improving on Nature", Wartburg College, Waverly, Iowa, September 26, 1976 [65 minutes], 1976 September 26; sound (Box 106, Tape 29)
  - Untitled lecture, sound (Box 106, Tape 30)
    Subjects include: nature vs. nurture and individuality and diversity of environments, December 7, 1966 [70 minutes].
  - Audio portion of film exerpts from, "The Unborn Patient", BBC-TV, Poor quality of film; film taken from reel to reel, made by Media Services, The Rockefeller University, 1987 [15 minutes], 1969 January 15; sound (Box 106, Tape 31)
  - Untitled speech, dedication of Rabbit Island, St. Regis Lake, Saranac Lake, NY, October 7, 1972. Introduction of Dr. Dubos made by Dr. George Mackaness, Director of The Trudeau Institute [20 minutes], 1972 October 7; sound (Box 106, Tape 32)
  - Reel to Reel "The Quality of Human Life", International Institute for the Reel to Study of Human Reproduction, Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons [30 minute speech by Dubos, 30 minute speech by Howard Taylor (director of the Institute), and 30 minute question/answer session; Total: 90 minutes], sound (Box 107, Tape 12)
  - Total of 10 [1 by Dubos] "Creative Adaptions to the Future", World Health in Human Perspective: A Series of Bicentennial Lectures (1976, Philadelphia, PA) by distinguished scholars, sound (Box 107, Tape 22)
    Speakers include: Philip H. Abelson, Victor P. Bond, Robert Coles, Cyril L. Comar, Allistair Cook, Charles E. Cornelius, Paul R. Ehrlich, Stuart C. Finch, Harry Harris, Jean Mayer, Wilson K. Talley, and Kenneth L. Vaux.
- (VIDEO CASSETTES), moving image
  - "Christopher Closeup: Beast or Angel", featuring Millicent Fenwick, Senator, N.J. January 30, 1975, The Christophers [U-Matic, 28 minutes], 1975 January 30; moving image (Box 108, Tape 1)
  - "I'd Rather Be Dead", Interview with Dubos re: teenage suicide in the NY Metropolitan area. WABC-TV Public Affairs, May 14, 1979 and May 6, 1982 [U-Matic, 25 minutes], 1979 May 14 1982 May 6; moving image (Box 108, Tape 2)
  - "Waksman Remembered", unedited remembrances of Waksman by Florence Tenney Starkey, Robert Starkey, H. Heukeleian, and Dubos (Waksman's graduate students during the 1920s). Waksman Institute of Microbiology, 1981 August 12; moving image (Box 108, Tape 3)
    [U-Matic, two video cassettes, VC-3a and VC-3b; 120 minutes].
  - MISSING, moving image (Box 108, Tape 4)
  - "A View for the Campus", interview. WJLT-TV, University of Tennessee, October 1981 [VHS; 28 minutes-poor quality], 1981 October; moving image (Box 108, Tape 5)
  - "René Dubos, Live at Five", interview. WNBC-TV [Dub], December 31, 1981 [missing sheet in finding aid], 1981 December 31; moving image (Tape 6)
  - Exerpt from "The Despairing Optimist", Interview, exerpt used at UN/René Dubos Forum, May 15, 1987. Bill Moyers' Journal #711, WNET-TV Channel 13 (PBS), filmed January 3, 1980, aired February 20, 1980 [U-Matic; 14 minutes], moving image (Box 109, Tape 7)
  - "Energy and the Way We Live". The introduction to a national issues forum, Spring 1980. Narrated by Bill Moyers; Dubos does not appear in the presentation, though his ideas and philosophies are the basis for this forum [U-Matic; 17 minutes], 1979; moving image (Box 109, Tape 8)
  - "Think Globally - Act Locally", Documentary on the success story of cleanup of Willamette River in Oregon and a René Dubos Forum in Corvallis. Oregon Educational and Public Broadcasting, December 30, 1980 [U-Matic; 29 minutes], 1980 December 30; moving image (Box 109, Tape 9)
  - MISSING, moving image (Box 109, Tape 10)